Finding Aid for Charles G. Overberger papers, 1957-1990
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Charles G. Overberger papers
1957-1990
Overberger, Charles G. (1920-1987)
97104 Aa 2
Professor of chemistry and vice president for research at University of Michigan. Includes alphabetical files, 1957-1983, containing correspondence, lectures and speeches, and other materials relating to his career and associations as a chemist; also professional files created since leaving his position as University of Michigan Vice President for Research.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
5 linear feet
The collection was donated by Dr. Charles Overberger (donor no. 8044 ) in May 1992.
No further additions to the records expected.
The collection is open without restriction.
Dr. Charles Gilbert Overberger, an educator and leader in the field of organic polymer chemistry, was born in the small town of Barnesboro, Pennsylvania, in 1920. In 1941, he graduated with a B.S. degree from Pennsylvania State University and then continued on to earn a Ph.D. from the University of Illinois in 1944, studying under the direction of Dr. Carl "Speed" Marvel.
After his formal academic training, Overberger held a postdoctoral fellowship at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1946 before obtaining the position of assistant professor at the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn in 1947. He quickly assumed roles of greater leadership by earning promotions to professor of Chemistry and associate director in 1951, chairman of the Department of Chemistry from 1955 to 1963, and then finally dean of Science and director of the Polymer Research Institute in 1964. He held this post at the Polytechnic Institute until coming to the University of Michigan as professor and chairman of the Department of Chemistry in 1967. At U of M Overberger was also charged with the responsibility of setting up the new Macromolecular Research Center. He accomplished this task with success and was rewarded for his efforts by being appointed vice-president of Research in 1972. In 1983, Dr. Overberger returned to the Department of Chemistry as a member of the faculty until his retirement in 1989.
Although Overberger held numerous administrative positions, both in educational institutions and in various professional organizations, he still found time to pursue his research interests in the fields of synthetic organic reaction mechanisms and polymer chemistry. These projects provided both biochemists and polymer chemists the understanding of basic conformational and structural principles of biopolymers. As a result, Overberger was invited to lecture throughout the world, worked as a consultant for industry and government, and won many prestigious awards, as well as the respect of his peers. His wife, Betty, accompanied him on many of his travels. Overberger also had four children, Erica, Carla, Charles Thomas, and Ellen Ann, from a previous marriage.
Dr. Overberger was a member of the American Chemical Society, the Chemical Society, the American Institute of Chemists, the American Association for the Advancement of Science, the Society of Chemical Industry, Alpha Chi Sigma, Phi Lambda Upsilon, and Sigma Zi. He was also a member of the Phi Eta Sigma, Phi Kappa Pi, and Sigma Pi and received honorary Doctor of Science degrees from Holy Cross College, Long Island University, and the Federal University of Rio de Janeiro. Awards include the New York Award of the American Institute of Chemists, the Witco Award in Polymer Chemistry of the American Chemical Society, The Distinguished Alumni Award of the Pennsylvania State University, The Charles Lathrop Parsons Award of the American Chemical Society, The Horace N. Potts Medal of the Franklin Institute, The International Award of the Society of Plastic Engineers, Michigan Scientist of the Year, the American Chemical Society Polymer Chemistry Division Award, and the American Chemical Society Paul S. Flory Polymer Education Award.
Throughout his career, Overberger always cherished his work as an educator, teaching graduate-level chemistry courses and mentoring students interested in polymer research. He also served as editor for several professional journals including the Journal of Polymer Science Advances in High Polymer Research and was the first editor for Macromolecular Syntheses. Time was also contributed as a member of advisory boards for the Polymer News, Macromolecules and, Organic Preparations and Procedures, International.
In 1987, as Overberger was preparing for his retirement from the University of Michigan, he was diagnosed with Parkinson's disease. While this did not initially restrict him from his educational and research activities, the disease's progression did eventually lead to the cessation of all professional activities. Charles Overberger died in 1997.
The papers of Dr. Charles G. Overberger are comprised of three series, Topical Files, Post Vice President of Research Activities, and Biographical Materials. These papers document his work as a professor, researcher, consultant, and expert in polymer chemistry, his administrative duties at the University of Michigan, and his career overall. The papers were originally filed and arranged by his various office assistants over the years and because of this constant attention to detail, have been preserved in the manner in which they arrived.
Subjects:
Overberger, C. G. (Charles Gilbert), 1920-; Chemistry, Organic.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Chemistry.
- Topical Files
  The Topical Files (4.5 linear feet) series contains papers dating from 1957 to 1983 and are arranged alphabetically by each individual's name or institution. Correspondence comprises the bulk of the records, as Overberger had personal as well as professional relationships with many prominent chemists in his field. Transcripts of several of Overberger's various talks can be found arranged alphabetically by institution under the heading of Talks. Correspondence found in the many files devoted to various institutions also illustrates his activities as a popular speaker on the topic of polymer chemistry. Several photographs of Overberger and his cohorts are also scattered throughout the collection and are noted in parentheses in the box listing.
  - A Miscellaneous, 1964-1981 (Box 1)
  - ACS Meeting-in-Miniature-Lecture (April 12, 1974) (Box 1)
  - ACS Visit-Antioch College (October 7, 1977), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - Ad Hoc Committee for a University Program for Students in the Medical Sciences, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Advanced Studies Institute-Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute (July 15-17, 1973 (Box 1)
  - Akron Summit Polymer Conference (September 9-10, 1976) (Box 1)
  - Alcoa Laboratories, 1978 (Box 1)
  - Alfrey, Turner, 1960-1980 (Box 1)
  - American Cyanamid Co.-Lecture (December 12, 1979) (Box 1)
  - ARCO Chemical Co.-Lecture (June 24, 1983), 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Arizona, University of-Lecture (October 13, 1972) (Box 1)
  - Army Research Office (United States) (September 13, 1972) (Box 1)
  - Asian Paint Company, 1968-1970 (Box 1)
  - Associated Universities, Inc.
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory (March 18, 1981), 1980-1981 (Box 1)
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory (April 6 & 7, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - Brookhaven National Laboratory-Report, 1983 (Box 1)
  - Auburn University-Lecture (April 25, 1978), 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - B Miscellaneous, 1966-1983 (Box 1)
  - B.F. Goodrich
    - Lecture (June 30, 1972) (Box 1)
    - Lecture (April 10, 1980) (Box 1)
  - Battellel ACS Symposium (May 8, 1979) (Box 1)
  - Big 10 Chairmen, 1971-1974 (Box 1)
  - Biological Chemistry Search Committee, 1969 (Box 1)
  - Boyer Banquet (February 6, 1975) (Box 1)
  - Brazil, Rio De Janeiro
    - Miscellaneous, 1976-1979 (Box 1)
    - Sempol II (October 25-31, 1980), 1976-1980 (Box 1)
  - Brazilian Academy of Sciences, 1979 (Box 1)
  - Brussels, Belgium Colloquium "150 Years Belgium" (November 12-14, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Bush, Larry, 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - C Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Case Western Reserve University, 1970-1977 (Box 1)
  - Cationic Polymerization, Fourth International Symposium (June 20-24, 1976), 1975-1976 (Box 1)
  - Chemical Society-Lecture (November 20-21, 1973) (Box 1)
  - Chemistry Department, 1927-1983; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Chemplex Corporation, 1967-1975 (Box 1)
  - Clarkson College, International Symposium on Solution Behavior of Surfactants (June 30-July 3, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 1)
  - Clarkston College of Technology-Lecture (March 31, 1975), 1974-1975 (Box 1)
  - Climax Molybdenum Co. (August 20, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Cohen, Irving, 1962-1967 (Box 1)
  - Cope, Arthur, 1963-1971 (Box 1)
  - Copyright Clearance Center (September 22, 178), 1977-1979 (Box 1)
  - Crist, Frederick, 1970 (Box 1)
  - D Miscellaneous, 1967-1981 (Box 1)
  - Dow Chemical, 1967-1981 (Box 1)
  - Dreyfus Laboratory, 1966-1971 (Box 1)
  - DuPont Company, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - DuPont Company-Lecture (May 19, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 1)
  - E Miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box 1)
  - Eastern Michigan University, 1968-1969 (Box 1)
  - Eastman Kodak Company-Lecture (April 8, 1983), 1982-1983 (Box 1)
  - Edgewood Arsenal-Chemical Systems Laboratory (January 25, 1980), 1979-1980 (Box 2)
  - Eirich, F.R. (Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn), 1963-1977 (Box 2)
  - Emerson, William S., 1972-1974 (Box 2)
  - Enzyme Engineering Conference (August 4, 1975) (Box 2)
  - ESSO Research and Engineering Co. (May 15 & 21, 1974) (Box 2)
  - Exxon CRL Polymer Science Review, 1978 (Box 2)
  - F Miscellaneous, 1970-1980 (Box 2)
  - Federal University of Rio (July 25-30, 1982) (Box 2)
  - Fettes, E.M., 1962-1969 (Box 2)
  - Flory, Paul, Dinner for-Carnegie Mellon University (June 17, 1975) (Box 2)
  - Franklin Institute, 1967 (Box 2)
  - Franklin Institute-Horace N. Potts Medal (November 10, 1982), 1982-1983 (Box 2)
  - Frisch, Kurt, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous, 1965-1983 (Box 2)
  - G Miscellaneous, 1962-1982 (Box 2)
  - Gaylord, Norman, 1958-1981 (Box 2)
  - General Electric
    - 1971-1972 (Box 2)
      (January 5, 1972)
    - 1976-1977 (Box 2)
      (January 20-21, 1977)
  - General Mills, 1972 (Box 2)
  - Goldman, James A., 1965-1969 (Box 2)
  - Goodman M.
    - Baekeland Award, 1966 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous, 1958-1978 (Box 2)
  - Gordan Research Conferences, 1968-1983; 13 folders (Box 2)
  - Gregor, Harry P., 1964-1978 (Box 2)
  - Guelph, University of (March 7-12, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - H Miscellaneous, 1968-1983 (Box 2)
  - I Miscellaneous, 1964-1979 (Box 2)
  - Immergut, Edmund H., 1963-1971 (Box 2)
  - Industrial Research Institute, 1969-1970 (Box 2)
  - International Minerals and Chemical Corp. (November 7, 1980) (Box 2)
  - Invitations, 1972-1983 (Box 2)
  - K Miscellaneous, 1970-1981 (Box 2)
  - Kargin, V.A., 1959-1966 (Box 2)
  - Katchalsky, A.-Symposium (February 3, 1973), 1972-1973 (Box 2)
  - Katchalsky, Ephraim Katzir (President of Israel), 1972-1983 (Box 2)
  - Kern, W., 1964-1972 (Box 2)
  - L Miscellaneous, 1967-1982 (Box 2)
  - Leibman, Joe, 1962-1972 (Box 2)
  - Loebl, Ernest M., 1962-1981 (Box 2)
  - Long Island University, 1968 (Box 2)
  - Louisiana State University (February 20, 1970), 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Lyon, France, International Symposium on Supported Fragments in Organic Chemicals (June 29-July 1, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 2)
  - M Miscellaneous, 1968-1983 (Box 3)
  - Macro Lab-North Campus, 1982 (Box 3)
  - Macromolecular Research Center, 1983 (Box 3)
  - Macromolecular Synthesis, 1966-1979; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Mandl, Ines, 1963-1978 (Box 3)
  - Manecke, Georg, 1964-1969 (Box 3)
  - Mano, Eloisa, 1978-1981; 2 folders (Box 3)
    (contains photographs)
  - Mark, Herman
    - Bust Presentation, 1960 (Box 3)
      (includes photo of Mark)
    - Correspondence, 1954-1982; 2 folders (Box 3)
      (contains photograph of Mark)
    - Interview, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
    - Priestly Medal Award, 1962-1967 (Box 3)
    - Symposium (May 27-28, 1965) (Box 3)
    - Symposium (May 3, 1975), 1974-1975 (Box 3)
    - Symposium (May 1, 1980) (Box 3)
    - Symposium (June 9, 1980) (Box 3)
    - TV Series, 1965-1966 (Box 3)
    - Willard Gibbs Award Dinner (May 16, 1975), 1973-1975 (Box 3)
    - Witco Chemical Award in Polymer Chemistry, 1962-1964 (Box 3)
  - Marvel, Carl (Speed)
    - First C.S. Marvel Lecture (April 28, 1982) (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous, 1959-1982 (Box 3)
      (contains photos)
    - Symposium-Alpha Sigma Chi (August 19, 1970) (Box 3)
    - Witco Chemical Award in Polymer Chemistry, 1963 (Box 3)
    - World Trade Center Symposium (March 11, 1983) (Box 3)
  - N Miscellaneous, 1983 (Box 3)
  - National Bureau of Standards-Lecture (May 14, 1982) (Box 3)
  - National Chemical Lab of India, 1968-1973 (Box 3)
  - National Research Council-Research Associationships Evaluation Panel (February 7, 1976), 1975-1977 (Box 3)
  - Natta, Giulio-Lecture to Honor (December 5, 1979) (Box 3)
  - Naval Research Labs, 1970-1979 (Box 3)
  - New York Academy of Science
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1978 (Box 3)
    - Polymer Science Section (March 25, 1981), 1980-1981 (Box 3)
  - Nobel Award, 1963-1977 (Box 3)
  - North Carolina State University
    - Miscellaneous, 1976 (Box 3)
    - School of Textiles (March 26-27, 1975), 1974-1976 (Box 3)
  - Nozakura, Shun-ichi, 1972-1973 (Box 3)
  - O Miscellaneous, 1969-1977 (Box 3)
  - Oakland University-Chemistry Seminar (December 1, 1982) (Box 3)
  - Okamura, Seizon, 1966-1971 (Box 3)
  - P Miscellaneous, 1965-1983 (Box 3)
  - Panel for Polymer Science and Engineering (POSIE), 1979-1981 (Box 3)
  - Pennsylvania State University (June 7, 1975), 1975-1976 (Box 3)
  - People's Republic of China, 1979-1982 (Box 3)
  - People's Republic of China (October 3-20, 1979) (Box 3)
  - Phelps Dodge Magnetic Wire Corp., 1970 (Box 3)
  - Plastic Engineers, Society of, 1964-1978 (Box 4)
  - Plastic Engineers, Society of, SPE International Award (May 9-10, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Plastics Institute of America, 1969 (Box 4)
  - Polish Academy of Sciences (May 1975), 1973-1975 (Box 4)
  - Polymer Research Institute Advisory Board (Univ. of Mass.), 1971-1980 (Box 4)
  - Polymer Science Advisory Board (Univ. of Conn.), 1981-1983 (Box 4)
  - R Miscellaneous, 1963-1983 (Box 4)
  - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute-Lecture (October 8, 1980), 1979-1981 (Box 4)
  - Research Club of the University of Michigan, 1967-1974 (Box 4)
  - Research Corporation, 1959-1976 (Box 4)
  - Roma and Haas Company, 1968-1970 (Box 4)
  - Rohm and Haas Spring House Labs-Lecture (June 23, 1983) (Box 4)
  - Romania Visit (May 18-28, 1972), 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - Rutgers University-Evaluation Chemistry Program (March 3, 1977), 1975-1977 (Box 4)
  - S Shell Development Company, 1967-1980 (Box 4)
  - Smets, Georges, 1967-1981 (Box 4)
  - Soviet Union (May 24-June 6, 1969), 1968-1969 (Box 4)
  - Stauffer Chemical Company (April 16, 1980) (Box 4)
  - Szmantz, Harry, 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - Szwarc Symposium (June 1, 1978) (Box 4)
  - Szwarc, Michael, 1957-1978 (Box 4)
  - T Miscellaneous, 1963-1982 (Box 4)
  - Talks
    - "ACS Publications,", undated (Box 4)
    - CCPA Subcommittee on Regulatory Practices, 1978 (Box 4)
    - "(The) Chemist and Public Policy,", 1969 (Box 4)
    - "(The) Chemist's Point of view as an Originator of the Input and a User of the Output,", 1970 (Box 4)
    - Cospup-Satcom Conference (June 25, 1967) (Box 4)
    - Couzens Program, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Dearborn Center Commencement, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Dedication Talk, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Dinners, undated (Box 4)
    - Donald E. Johnson Lecture-Introduction (December 8, 1972) (Box 4)
    - "Education in Polymer Chemistry" or "Macromolecular,", 1969 (Box 4)
    - Highway Safety Research Institute-Welcome, 1974 (Box 4)
    - "Information System of ACS,", 1967-1968 (Box 4)
    - Manpower Projections (October 30-31, 1975) (Box 4)
    - Message to ACS Council, 1967 (Box 4)
    - Minneapolis ACS Meeting (April 1969), 1968-1969 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, circa 1967-1975 (Box 4)
    - Office of Naval Research-Project SQUID, 1974 (Box 4)
    - President's Meeting, undated (Box 4)
    - "Primary Publications,", 1970 (Box 4)
    - "Research Views in Chemistry,", undated (Box 4)
    - "Responsibilities of Chemists in Our Environment of Social Change,", 1970 (Box 4)
    - "Science and Education in the ACS,", 1971 (Box 4)
    - Student Affiliate Group, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Talks (Box 4)
    - Tennessee-Eastman Company-Lecture (April 14, 1978), 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - "Trends in Macromolecular Education,", 1971 (Box 4)
    - University of Michigan State of the University Debates, 1973 (Box 4)
    - University Press Club, 1973 (Box 4)
  - U Miscellaneous, 1964-1977 (Box 4)
  - University of Akron
    - Lecture (April 6, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous, 1977 (Box 4)
    - Polymer Science Series (April 8, 1971), 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - University of Alabama
    - Lecture (November 20, 1970) (Box 4)
    - Lecture (January 7, 1971), 1970-1971 (Box 4)
  - University of Arizona
    - Lecture (November 2 1977), 1977-1978 (Box 4)
    - Lecture (January 21, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - University of Detroit
    - Polymer Conference Series, 1974-1981 (Box 4)
    - Polymer Conference Series (May 2, 1977), 1976 (Box 4)
    - Polymer Conference Series (May 7, 1978), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Polymer Conference Series (May 7-11, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - University of Kentucky, 1978 (Box 4)
  - University, Louisiana State, 1977 (Box 4)
  - University of Mary, 1967 (Box 4)
  - University of Massachusetts
    - Lecture (November 10, 1976) (Box 4)
    - Lecture (March 2, 1979 (Box 4)
  - University of North Carolina-Lecture (January 24-25, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - University, North Carolina State, Symposium of George Gold Finger (June 2, 1977) (Box 4)
  - University of North Dakota (February 25, 1972), 1971-1972 (Box 4)
  - University of Notre Dame-Lecture (November 1, 1978) (Box 4)
  - University of Southern Mississippi-Lecture (April 23, 1982), 1981-1982 (Box 4)
  - University of Tennessee (January 16, 1979), 1978-1979 (Box 4)
  - University of Wisconsin-Milwaukee, 1977 (Box 4)
  - U.S.-Japan Polymer Synthesis Seminar (2nd.) (August 20-24, 1978) (Box 4)
  - V Miscellaneous, 1969-1970 (Box 5)
  - Valparaiso University-Lecture (December 10, 1970) (Box 5)
  - Virginia Commonwealth University (October 8, 1976) (Box 5)
  - Visitors
    - Alfrey, Turner, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Calkins, William H., 1973 (Box 5)
    - Challa, G., 1973 (Box 5)
  - Visitors (cont.)
    - Chinese Chemistry Group (includes photographs), 1977 (Box 5)
    - Corett, Ruth, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Emerson, William, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Goodman, Murray, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Japanese Scientist Group (Dr. Imahori), 1974 (Box 5)
    - Jedlinski, Zbigniew, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Kabariov, Victor A., 1970-1976 (Box 5)
    - Lien, Arthur, 1974 (Box 5)
    - Mano, Eloisa, 1970-1973 (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1968-1982; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Pickerel, Luther, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Shaw, Robert A., 1974 (Box 5)
    - Sigwalt, Pierre, 1973 (Box 5)
    - Zaikov, G.E., 1973 (Box 5)
  - W Miscellaneous, 1969-1982 (Box 5)
  - Wayne State University, 1967-1972 (Box 5)
  - Welch Foundation Meeting (November 17, 1982) (Box 5)
  - West Virginia University, 1979 (Box 5)
  - Westinghouse Electrical Corp., R&D Center (October 24-25, 1978), 1978-1979 (Box 5)
  - Wichterle, Otto, 1960-1970 (Box 5)
  - Wright State University (Box 5)
  - Evaluation (April 25, 1979) (Box 5)
  - Lecture (February 10, 1978) (Box 5)
  - XYZ Miscellaneous, 1966-1981 (Box 5)
  - Xerox Corporation
    - May 12, 1977 (Box 5)
    - June 10, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Yugoslavia Visit, 1975-1976 (Box 5)
- Post Vice President of Research Activities
  The files found in the Post Vice President of Research Activities (0.5 linear feet) series date from 1984 to 1987 and are arranged in a somewhat chronological fashion. These files also contain mostly correspondence as Overberger arranged for his retirement and handled his professional chemist responsibilities.
  - Correspondence
    - 1984 (Box 5)
    - 1985, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1986, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1987, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - 1988 (Box 5)
    - Department of Chemistry, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
    - Journal, 1987-1989 (Box 5)
  - Stille, John, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Symposium on Polymer Synthesis, Characterization and Properties (September 8-9, 1988) (Box 5)
  - Wilson, Linda, 1986-1987 (Box 5)
- Biographical Materials
  The Biographical Materials (0.25 linear feet) series contains articles and newspaper clippings about Dr. Overberger, correspondence about his reassignments throughout his career and his retirement, a list of publications by Dr. Overberger, and booklets from the tribute in 1985 and the symposium in 1990, both held in his honor. Also included are dated and undated photographs of Dr. Overberger teaching, on trips to Japan in 1964 and 1982, and multiple portraits.
  - Articles and clippings (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Reassignments, 1967-1972 (Box 5)
  - Correspondence: Retirement, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Photographs (Box 5)
  - Publications list (Box 5)
  - Symposium, 1990 (Box 5)
  - Tribute, 1985 (Box 5)
Related Material
Additional papers documenting Overberger's activities as a member of professional organizations were donated to the Beckman Center for the History of Chemistry located in Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, in 1992.
For more information about Dr. Overberger's career see the records of the University of Michigan, Vice President of Research also housed at the Bentley Historical Library.